Ludovic Leconte, Engineer

Nationality: French Birthdate: 11/11/1979

SERPICO Team, Inria - Curie Institute, UMR144 CNRS. Email: ludovic.leconte@curie.fr

12 rue Lhomond, 75005 Paris, FRANCE Phone: +33 685310257

My research experience ranges from construction/running of advanced optical microscopes to processing/analyzing imaging data together with cell biology applications, as well as visualization of 3D+time data. Working experiences in different countries enable me to work independently and as part of international environments Have the expertise on facilities more 10 years. Since two years, I have been in charge of the cell culture and the preparation of samples for our team

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Engineer – Team SERPICO Paris with Dr. C. Kervrann and Dr. J. Salamero,

09/2018 up to now

French National Institute for Research in Digital Science and Technology (Inria) & CNRS-Institut Curie, Paris, France

Project: Acquisition, analysis, and visualization of 3D Dynamic cellular imaging of Endosomal Membranes Associated to Mitochondria I was also responsible of setting up a Lattice Light Sheet Microscope and the Multi-Angle-Ring TIRF on the PICT-IBISA imaging facility at Curie Institute, which is part of the France BioImaging National Infrastructure at 20% of my time by project.

My project in team is evaluate the putative interactions od the different constituents of the endocytic pathway with Mitochondria In LLSM. I compared them and used the trackmate software and I visualized NAPARI visualization was used to check this tracking. In addition, I collaborate in the development of machine learning-driven navigation and interaction techniques for 3D+Time data enabling the analysis of localized intra-cellular events (endocytosis and exocytosis) and cell processes (migration, division, etc.). I am in charge of the exploitation of biological models (cell culture, transfections, data acquisition). I manage my project related to the theme of the team, I take care of orders, and work closely collaboration with colleagues from the Rennes team to develop new tools.

Facility Engineer - PICT-IBISA-Institute Curie directed by Dr. J.Salamero

03/2013 - 09/2018

On the PICT imaging platform at the Curie Institute under the supervision of Umr 144. My schedule is divided into several functions, 60% of the time on the platform and 40% on system development.

On the platform, I was in charge of so-called conventional systems (video microscope, spinning, epi-fluorescence) but more advanced systems (SIM, Live SR) and I took care of user training.

More regularly, I made a metrology of the systems

I was also in charge of development on more sophisticated systems (EasySPIM, Multi-Photon, Frap-W1, LLSM that I had to set up before it was opened by project on the platform.

I also led demonstrations for the platform in order to make new proposals for imaging and application modalities (sample transparency, automation, etc.).

I was responsible for the high-resolution 3D laser printer platform. (Solidwork software referent for designer of 3D parts for microscopy).

Facility Engineer -BIOEMERGENCES Directed by Dr. N. Peyrieras

01/2011 - 02/2013

On the facility, I m charge in Maintenance and development of biphoton microscopes and the first prototype in france of the DSLM (Digital Scanned Laser light sheet fluorescence) microscope. I was also in charge of the metrology of its systems
I was in charge of setting up an optical coupling of two Bi-photon lasers to send it to two SP5s. The power system had to be motorised and controllable on the acquisition pcs of the two systems.

I set up new protocols for the use of its developments, I was the referent of the commands and the data acquired on the systems. I developed new techniques for the preparation of samples for the DSLM that were suitable for large samples.

Engineer's Assistant–LULI (LABORATORY FOR THE USER OF INTENSE LASERS) Polytechnic School 09/2008 – 12/2010 My first mission was the operation of high power laser chains (Kj). I had to take care of the alignment, the energy measurement (calorimeters), the calibration control before each shot. I also worked on the archiving of the shooting data, preparation of the experiments to the control of the optics (spectrophotometer, interferometer, bidimensional measurement....)

I also had to check that the whole chain was under a secondary vacuum. Finally, I worked with very specific instrumentation of the chain (deformable mirror, Hartmann, Shearring...)

My first mission was to assemble lasers for dermatology and ophthalmology. I also had to do a metrology on the optical and electronic components before starting the laser assembly. Then I had to follow a very strict protocol to check the alignment and the characterization of the beam (polarization, M², imaging, energy, stability...)

Finally I collaborated with the R&D and the industrialization for the improvement of the fiber laser so that it can be commercialized

EDUCATION

2019	CNAM (conservatoire des arts et metiers) Unit on Molecular Biology
	evening classes, Paris
2019	Master Sciences, Technology, Health, Mention Biology Health
	Rouen Mention Bien
2004	Professional degree in electronics and optics for telecommunications
	Limoges, Mention assez bien
2003	BTS in optical engineering Option photonics in alternance in Angoulême
	Companie Highwave Optical Technologie specialist in component and fibers optical for the
	telecommunication in Paris and Lannion

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] S. Prigent, C. A. Valades-Cruz, L. Leconte, J. Salamero and C. Kervrann. STracking: a free and open-source python library for particle tracking and analysis, 2022 (Bioiformatics)
- [2] A. Salomon, C. Valades-Cruz, L. Leconte, C. Kervrann. Dense mapping of intracellular diffusion and drift from single particle tracking data analysis, 2022 (in preparation)
- [3] Sylvain Prigent.*, Hoai-Nam Nguyen.*, **Ludovic Leconte**, Valades-Cruz, C. A, Bassam Hajj, Salamero, J., Kervrann, C SPITFIR(e): A supermaneuverable algorithm for restoring 2D-3D fluorescence images and videos, and background subtraction. bioRxiv (2022).
- [4] Prigent, S.*, Valades-Cruz, C. A.*, **Leconte, L.***, Maury, L., Salamero, J., Kervrann, C. BioImageIT: Open-source framework for integration of image data-management with analysis. bioRxiv (2021) [Manuscript under revision in Nat. Methods.]
- [5] Cesar Augusto Valades Cruz, **Ludovic Leconte**, Christian Wunder, Charles Kervrann, Ludger Johannes, et al.. 3D tracking of endocytic and exocytic events using lattice light sheet microscopy. QBI 2020 Quantitative Biolmaging Conference, Jan 2020, Oxford, United Kingdom. (hal-03087217)
- [6] Antoine Salomon, Cesar Augusto Valades Cruz, **Ludovic Leconte**, Charles Kervrann. Dense mapping of intracellular diffusion and drift from single-particle tracking data analysis. IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), May 2020, Barcelona, Spain. (hal-03087048
- [7] Diana Vargas-Hurtado, Jean-Baptiste Brault, Tristan Piolot, **Ludovic Leconte**, Nathalie da Silva, et al.. Differences in Mitotic Spindle Architecture in Mammalian Neural Stem Cells Influence Mitotic Accuracy during Brain Development. Current Biology CB, Elsevier, 2019, 29 (18), pp.2993-3005.e9.(10.1016/j.cub.2019.07.061). (hal-02400423) 2019
- [8] Ludovic Leconte, Francois Waharte, Jean Salamero EasySPIM: AN Easy Light Sheet Microscope Imaging & Microscopy WILEY-Volume20-JUIN
- [9] Marthiens, Diana Vargas-Hurtado, Jean-Baptiste Brault, Krndija, D; Tristan Piolot, **Ludovic Leconte**, Pennetier, C; Nathalie da Silva, et al.. Noncell autonomous spindle morphology contributes to mitotic vulnerability of embryonic neural stem cells in mammals. Molecular Biology of the Cell, Meeting Abstract P2873 Index 2018-12-15
- [10] Venzac B; Madoun R; Benarab T; Monnier S; Cayrac F; Myram S; **Leconte, L**; Amblard F; Viovy JL; Descroix S. Engineering small tubes with changes in diameter for the study of kidney cell organization BIOMICROFLUIDICS Volume: 12 Issue: 2; Article Number: 024114 DOI: 10.1063/1.5025027 2018
- [11] Annexin-A5 organized in 2D-network at the plasmalemma eases human trophoblast fusion By: Degrelle, Severine A.; Gerbaud, Pascale; Leconte, Ludovic; et al. SCIENTIFIC REPORTS Volume: 7 Article Number: 42173 Published: FEB 2017
- [12] Severine Degrelle, Pascale Gerbaud, **Ludovic Leconte**, Fátima Ferreira, Guillaume Pidoux. Annexin-A5 organized in 2D-network at the plasmalemma eases human trophoblast fusion OPEN. Scientific Reports, Nature Publishing Group, 2017, 7 (1), pp.42173. (10.1038/srep42173). (inserm-02440462) 2017
- Lauriane Velot, Angie Molina, Sylvie Rodrigues-Ferreira, Anne Nehlig, Benjamin, Pierre Bouchet, et al.. Negative regulation of EB1 turnover at microtubule plus ends by interaction with microtubule-associated protein ATIP3. Oncotarget, Impact journals, 2015, 6 (41) pp.43557-43570. (10.18632/oncotarget.6196). (inserm-01223890) 2015

ADDITIONAL SKILLS

Computational Languages & Tools: Python, LabVIEW, Java, ImageJ/FIJI, Icy, IMARIS, Prism, Microsoft Excel, Zen, Solidworks, FreeCad, Matamorph, BioImageIt

Microscope: Spinning, LiveSR, Confocal scanning, STED, SIM, SPIM, Bi-Photon, FRAP/FLIP, LLSM, Epifluorescence Microscopy, Nomarski.

Acquisition software: Metamorph, Leica, ZEISS, 3i, Nikon, STEDYCON, Homemade Software, open Iris

Mechanical's labs: metal turning machine, milling machine, laser cut, 3D printing (Polyjet, FDM, 3D SLA), Hot wire bending machine for plastics processing

Ongoing PROJECTS & COLLABORATIONS

- 2022 Polarization Microscopy for Imaging of Membrane Organization (PoMIMO)
 - <u>Objective:</u> Create a new imaging approach that will not only provide novel information about endocytosis, but will have the potential to be applied to all topics where the spatial and molecular organization of lipids/proteins defines both the structure and function of these assemblies (i.e. mitochondria cristae, MAMs....) in reconstituted systems and in living cells.
- 2019 Project NAVISCOPE: image-guided navigation and visualization of large data sets in live cell imaging and microscopy. Acquisition des données en LLSM et test des données , deux journées de demonstration
- 2019 **Project BioImageIT: open-source integrator for Image DATA management and analysis.** Ongoing project of the Serpico TEAM in the frame of the NRI (National Research Infrastructure France BioImaging) and dissemination toward the 18 Imaging Facilities that constitute the Core of the Infrastructure.
- 2017 Project ANR: Data Assimilation and Lattice Light Sheet imaging for endocytosis/exocytosis pathway modeling in the whole cell (DALLISH). Collaboration to investigate endocytosis pathways in the whole cell using 3D single particle tracking.
- 2013 Project EasySPIM: An Easy Light Sheet Microscope Optimizing Light Sheet Microscopy at an Imaging Facility (CelTysPhyBio). Design and production of a light sheet miscroscope to make it available on the platform

Conference

- **Biolmage Informatics.** Poster presentation: Biolmage-IT _Integration of data-management with analysis Ludovic Leconte, Sylvain Prigent, Léo Maury César Augusto Valades Cruz, Jean Salamero Charles Kervrann
- **2020 FOM (Focus On Microscopy)in Japan.** Oral presentation accepted but cancelled due to Covid Live Cell Imaging of Membrane Recycling Using Lattice Light Sheet Microscopy and Multi-Angle (Ma) TIRF Microscopy [PDF]. L. Leconte, C.A. Valades-Cruz, C. Kervran, J. Salamero (Institut Curie, France)
- **2019 ELMI meeting, Brno, Czech Republic Lightning Talk:** Implementation of a commercial Lattice Light Sheet Microscope (LLSM) in an Imaging Facility (PICT-IBiSA) Ludovic Leconte, Cesar Augusto Valades Cruz, Jean Salamero
- **2018 LSFM** in Frankfurt , Light Sheet Microscopy Conference, 4-6 December 2019, Germany Implementation of a commercial Lattice Light Sheet Microscope (LLSM) in an Imaging Facility (PICT-IBISA)
- **FOM in Bordeaux en 2017**, PiCT-IBiSA: DEVELOPMENTS ON A MULTI-SCALE IMAGING PLATFORM; V.Fraisier,L.* Leconte,L*.Sengmanivong, M. Irondelle, F. Waharte, J. SalameroCell and Tissue Imaging Core Facility-IBiSA. UMR144-CNRSInstitut Curie(France)
- **FOM in Sydney**, OPTIMIZING LIGHT SHEET MICROSCOPY FOR MULTI-COLOR IMAGING OF VARIABLE SIZE SAMPLES ON AN OPEN IMAGING FACILITYLudovic Leconte, François Waharte, Jean Salamero

Other

- -ELUC in The National Committee for Scientific Research in section 22 and CID 54 2016-2021
- -Leading and federating **a working group of the RTMFM** (Réseau Technologique de Microscopie de Fluorescence Multidimensionnelle) of the CNRS, the **GT.ALL** (Architecture and Free Software working group). Creation of two documents "
- Leading and participating in the **Light Sheet Community working group** (international network group sharing knowledge and know-how on light sheet technology), created in 2020.
- Editing of online courses, "you tube" channel of the National Infrastructure France BioImaging (FBI) (**Working Group "Light Sheet Microscopy"**) and setting up an INSERM workshop (2022) on light sheet microscopy with the FBI Light Sheet Microscopy Working Group
- Animation and realisation of workshops on the CNRS MIFOBIO thematic school every two years